BETH: The world can seem a really
unpredictable and confusing place to
Individuals with autism, and they can
find any kind of change difficult.
They often develop routines and
rituals as strategies they can use,
to cope with confusing sounds and
sights, events, people and places.
JOE: They often prefer to have a daily
routine so that they know what is going
to happen every day, travelling the same
way to and from school or work, or eating
exactly the same food for breakfast.
BETH: Some individuals may find
minor changes upsetting like the
positioning of simple things around
the house or introducing something new.
Others find big events which create
major changes and upheaval distressing,
like going on holiday, starting a
new school or moving to a new house.
JOE: Some autistic people manage their
behaviour by using daily timetables to
help them see the structure of their day.
They often have a need for structured
routine around daily activities such as
meals or bedtime and routines can become
almost ritualistic in nature, followed
precisely with great attention to detail.
BETH: Some have rigid preferences
about things like food, such as always
wanting the same cereal or even only
eating food of a certain colour.
Some may only wear clothes
made from specific fabrics
or again of a certain colour.
JOE: Others find the need for
routine and sameness can go so
far, that it becomes an obsession.
People's dependence on routines can
increase during times of change, stress
or illness and may even become more
dominant or elaborate at these times.
BETH: Individuals with Autism can
find changes to their routines
difficult, but they can be prepared
for change and supported through it.